Okay, בוקר טוב *boker tov*. So today's דף *daf* is כג *chaf
gimmel*. We start with the משנה mishna. *mishna* on the bottom of
כד עמוד amud ב *chaf daled amud beis*. We had just had
a very dense, if you could judge from תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, discussion
about the nature of the גט get, *get*, the שטר *shtar* for
according to Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Meir, right, this is the debate
that runs through the מסכת *masechet* about the nature of a גט
get. *get*. If you say עדי חתימה chatima. כרתי *edei chatima karsi*,
you focus on the signatures and that turns it into a גט
get *get*. So on the one hand that led to a discussion
earlier that the גט get. *get* should have to, can't be attached
for Rabbi Meir, that means that it can't be מחובר *mechubar*. That
doesn't, it's not a problem in the writing, it's only a problem
in the signing, whereas for Rabbi Eliezer who focuses on the witnesses
when it's given, the writing aspect is on the actual writing of
the גט get. *get*, not the signatures. And then the מחובר *mechubar*
problem is when it's being written. Similarly we had a discussion about
a גט get. *get* written on page, on a document that was
forgeable, that you could erase and it would, it was already written
on something erased so it would not look like something had gone
wrong if you erase what had been written there because even the
signatures were on erased background. So for Rabbi Meir who focuses on
the signing, what that means is that he defines the גט get
*get* as a, as a part of the גט get. *get*'s very
definition is something that testifies because it emphasizes the עדות *edus* and
the signatures of the גט get. *get* that it testifies in writing
to what happened. So if that testimony it's no longer testifying because
it's something that's forgeable and therefore it's questionable what it is, did
it really say and is it really saying, it stops being a
גט get *get* for Rabbi Meir. So for Rabbi Meir even if
it was written on an erased background, even if it was given
in the presence of עדים edim. *edim*, it's no longer a גט
get *get*. And even if you have no question what actually happened,
it's not a גט get *get*. Part of the definition of it
as a גט get *get* is something that has written testimony and
in that case it's not considered to actually be testifying to anything.
Whereas for Rabbi Eliezer, it's not true. The testimony aspect is separate
from the גט get, *get*. It's the witnesses that are seeing it
being given. So even if it's written on a forgeable background, it's
still a legitimate גט get *get*. It doesn't have to testify to
anything and it's okay. And as far as how do you know
what happened, so maybe you actually ask the עדים eidim *edim*. But
how you know what happened is independent from whether it serves as,
it functions as an instrument of divorce and as a גט get
*get*. And that's a difference between a שטר קנין shtar kinyan *shtar
kinyan* when the document is serving as an instrument to change status
as opposed to a שטר ראיה shtar ra'aya, *shtar raya* when it's
serving as evidence. And for Rabbi Eliezer you can really separate those
identities and something could be a שטר קנין *shtar kinyan* without being
a שטר ראיה shtar ra'aya *shtar raya*. Therefore it could even be
written on a forgeable background. So that's another very important and significant
debate. And then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ended with the question about
whether maybe Rabbi Eliezer would concede that it have to be, you
know, viable written testimony by שאר שטרות *shar shtarot*, other שטרות *shtarot*.
And the question is what is meant by other שטרות *shtarot*. It
could mean that it means other שטרות *shtarot* that are שטר ראיה
shtar ra'aya, *shtar raya*, like that I borrowed money from you, for
that to serve as a שטר *shtar*, obviously it can't be written
on a forgeable background. There it really is, if it's serving only
as a ראיה ra'aya, *raya*, then it has to be legitimate valid
meaningful written testimony. And that's certainly how תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is inclined.
The simple sense of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is that it's a
unique point about גט get *get*. In גט get. *get* you can
separate those two identities. It can serve as an instrument as a
שטר קנין *shtar kinyan* without being a שטר ראיה ra'aya, *shtar raya*.
But with something else, let's say it was freeing my slave, right,
and the גט get *get* and the שטר *shtar* actually effected the
change of status. Or let's say I was selling you my plot
of land and I said שדי מכורה לך *sadi mechura lach*. That's
a case where it's a שטר קנין *shtar kinyan*, but maybe there
Rabbi Eliezer would say that for there to function as a שטר
קנין *shtar kinyan*, it also has to be a שטר ראיה *shtar
raya*. There those identities are intertwined and maybe it's saying that only
by גט get *get* does he allow it to be one without
the other. So that's not clear in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but
conceptually this is a really important point. That sometimes the issue of
כתיבה ketiva וחתימה *kesiva vechasima* that we focus on in Rabbi Meir
and Rabbi Eliezer is when the תורה *Torah* makes a demand about
how it's written, like it not being written במחובר *b'mechubar* or it
be written לשמה lishma, *lishmah*. Does that focus on the writing or
the signing? But to another in a deeper way it might be
that the debate is whether to what degree is a גט get.
*get* supposed to be written testimony, is it supposed to be a
שטר ראיה *shtar raya* and if so if it's forgeable it's not
a גט get. *get* at all regardless of what happened and if
we can prove what happened. Or is a גט get *get* really
just completely a שטר קנין *shtar kinyan* and does not have to
be written testimony at all and therefore even written on a forgeable
background. So a very fundamental debate and then similarly how do you
think about other שטרי קנין *shtarei kinyan* like שחרור *shichrur* and selling
a field and to what degree does that also have to be
a שטר ראיה *shtar raya* or not.
Yes Rabbi Do, clarification questions. One is what does Rabbi Eliezer do
when there is an ערעור *irur* of גט get אשה *get isha*.
Yeah, so you go get the עדים eidim, *edim* that were physically
present.
That's your only recourse.
He can't rely on the שטר *shtar*. Well actually no, I should
stop and say that and just to further... further complicate things, so
this will get you a little crazy, but there's ways in which
one position might hold of the other. So for example, there are
ראשונים rishonim, that think that well not only ראשונים, rishonim it's generally
assumed that if it's written on a non-forgeable background, it's a standard
type of a גט, get, then in that case while רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer does not require it to be a שטר ראיה, it
can function as a שטר ראיה under most circumstances. So if it's
written not on a non-forgeable background, you can actually use the written
signatures. You don't need to get the עדים. eidim If you don't
have them it'll still be good, but if you do have it,
it can function in that way. Some ראשונים rishonim go even further
and say that when you have written signatures for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, you don't even need physical witnesses to be present when it's
being given over. Those written witnesses not only can serve as a
ראיה, they can serve as the witnesses to the giving of the
גט. get, Okay, but
so it might in many cases, it could function just like רבי
מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's גט get, would function, but nevertheless, it doesn't have
to function that way.
Yeah. The second one is when we make this distinction between שטר
קנין and ראיה, between כתיבה and חתימה. chatima, Yeah. So what role
does the מסירה mesira play in this?
Well,
it has to be given over and obviously, that's נתן. natan. So
for it's generally assumed that for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the signed
witnesses signatures function to be the witnesses in the giving over. And
you don't need witnesses external to the גט. get. For רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, since the emphasis is
on the מסירה, mesira, not on the חתימה, you need witnesses to
be present external to the גט. get, Okay, so that's generally assumed
although again as I said, it gets complicated because some ראשונים assume
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say if you had signatures and
it was on a good background, it was not forgeable, they can
function for the physical presence of the witnesses. And just to complicate
it further, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that even for רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that demands the signatures, that's only to make it into
a גט. get. But when you give it over, you need actual
physical witnesses present external to it. So רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer?
Exactly. So there's a lot of crisscrossing, it gets very confusing, but
the most clear issue is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer demands when
it says וכתב, v'chatav, those demands focus on the writing and רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says they focus on the signing. And that for
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer as this גמרא Gemara makes clear, it can
function as a גט get, without being a שטר ראיה, without serving
also to testify as written testimony. So that I just wanted to
spend a few minutes reviewing that because that was really key and
to some degree we're going to continue
with the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir debate in
the next משנה. mishna. So let's look now at the next משנה.
mishna Okay, and the big תוספות Tosafot here is really on this
next משנה mishna not on what we just discussed. הכל כשרים לכתוב
את הגט. Hakol k'sherim lichtov et haget. Everybody can write a גט.
get אפילו חרש שוטה וקטן. Afilu cheresh shoteh v'katan. Even a deaf-mute,
somebody who is not of right mind, like mentally ill, or what
have you in a very particular way, somebody who does have a
hard time processing reality
is a שוטה shoteh and a minor. All these people are considered
to be not בני דעת, bnei da'at, people who normally cannot make
them a שליח, shaliach, an agent, they cannot normally execute legally binding
acts, and nevertheless they can write a גט. get So how they
can write a גט Get? is pretty bizarre because you would think
that you need כוונה kavana of לשמה, lishma maybe the סופר sofer
has to be a שליח shaliach of the husband.
So one easy way of understanding this
is that this is the גמרא'ס, Gemara's, but the simplest way based
on the information we have so far is that this is רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir who does not require the writing to be done
properly, only the signing. And if you'll remember the previous, first of
all סתם משנה stam mishna is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. And if
you remember the previous משנה mishna? said if you wrote a גט
Get on מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka as long as you signed it
after you detached the thing, you're okay. Right? Remember that previous משנה?
mishna So the simple sense is our משנה mishna. assumes that bottom
line what matters is the signing. It's a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
position. So if bottom line matters the signing, heck you can just
print your גט Get, off of a computer, just get the right
people to sign it. It doesn't matter how it's being written. Okay?
Now True like we have the, right, גוד אומר וגוד אחית?
Gud omer v'gud achit? Well, okay the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to get
to that but that's not in the משנה. mishna Okay, and the
משנה'ס mishna's consistent with the previous משנה mishna that the emphasis is
on the signing and not on the writing. האשה כותבת את
גיטה והאיש כותב את שוברו. Ha'isha kotevet et gita v'ha'ish kotev et
shovro. A woman could write her own גט Get? and a man
could write the receipt of having received the כתובה. ketuba. Now how
could they do that? You write your own גט, Get, right? You
cut out, you know, that makes things convenient. So the משנה mishnah
ends by saying שאין קיום הגט אלא בחותמיו. She'ein kiyum haget ela
b'chotamav. What validates the גט Get is the signatures. Again, emphasis on
signatures. So it doesn't matter who's doing the writing. You know, a
woman can't use it to misrepresent and claim she got a גט
Get? when she didn't because who cares about who wrote the actual
text, it doesn't mean anything until it's signed and the key is
getting witnesses to sign it. Okay, so that's why A, we're not
concerned that she'll misrepresent or that the man will misrepresent that he's
paid the כתובה ketubah when he didn't, because who cares what you
wrote without the signatures? That's just running something off your computer. It
doesn't become it's not meaningful until you actually get it signed, and
witnesses won't sign it unless it's actually being done properly, until it's
actually being handed from the husband to the wife, or they won't
sign his receipt until he actually witnessed him paying off his כתובה.
ketubah. Okay, so that's in terms of that it won't get abused,
you know, won't get misrepresented. But the other point is, is that
that's why we don't care who does the writing, even a חרש
שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve'katan. It's all about the signing. So the
simple sense of this משנה mishnah is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, like
the previous משנה mishnah about whether it's when it was written on
מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, it's not a problem as long as it's
signed after it's detached. So that was that's what we would say.
The גמרא Gemara is going to try to make it work for
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, but the simple sense of the whole משנה
mishnah and the previous משנה Mishnah is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
it all focuses on the signatures.
And לשמה lishma, is also on the signatures, not on the writing.
It's just that for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the וכתב vechataf of
the פסוק, pasuk, וכתב לה ספר כריתות vechataf lah sefer keritut means
וחתם, vechatam, that it becomes a גט Get through the signing. Okay,
so it's all about the signatures for רבי
מאיר.
Rabbi
Meir.
It's grounded because most people couldn't write.
Well, it's true. Okay, I understand that you're getting a חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan to write. Okay, okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, let's see what the גמרא Gemara. says.
So that's the simple sense, and the גמרא Gemara will have an
opinion that this is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But interestingly, the גמרא
Gemara initially assumes that this is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Maybe well,
well, let's take a look. Let's read the גמרא. gemara Partly it
might have to do with of what we said about the previous
thing about writing on detachable background was רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So
the גמרא gemara says, והלא לאו בני דעה נינהו? vehala lav bnei
de'ah ninhu? How can חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan write it?
They're not considered to be בני דעה. bnei de'ah. Their intent is
not considered to do something לשמה, lishma, you know, they're not le-
they're not legal adults, they can't execute, you know, sort of legal
acts, and here they can't write, presumably they can't write לשמה, lishma,
they don't have they're not considered to have proper intent. They're talking
about the woman? No, no, no, we're on חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh
shoteh ve'katan. אמר רב הונא והוא שהיה גדול עומד על גביו. Amar
Rav Huna vehu shehaya gadol omed al gabav. So like Michael anticipated,
we're talking that there's somebody standing over them and supervising. Now, תוספות
Tosafot points out that you have different scenarios of supervision. In the
case of שחיטה, shechita, גדול עומד על גביו gadol omed al gabav
is less of somebody is actually instructing them and more somebody is
just observing that it was done technically that it was done technically
correct, because by שחיטה shechita all that matters is that it was
performed in a technically correct way. Here where the idea is that
you have to write it with the right intent, גדול עומד על
גביו, gadol omed al gabav, תוספות Tosafot says, means that you're like
directly instructing the person as they're doing it, which also for תוספות
Tosafot addresses the question of שוטה, shoteh, because שוטה, shoteh, thank you,
is the case where normally we think that it's hardest to assume
that you can get the person to do it with the right
with the right intent. But תוספות Tosafot says, maybe in the case
of directly standing over and instructing, that's why we're suggesting that it
can work even for the everybody every member of that trio of
the חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve'katan. The other point that תוספות
Tosafot makes is that here it's better than other cases where we
don't have גדול עומד על גביו. gadol omed al gabav. Part of
this תוספות Tosafot is figuring out why does גדול עומד על גביו
gadol omed al gabav work here where it doesn't work in other
cases? And he says part of it is because you can actually
observe from what the person is doing whether they followed instructions or
not. Write the word לאה בת רחל, Leah bat Rachel, and he
writes לאה בת רחל. Leah bat Rachel. You know, write this word
and they write that word. So is it possible that they're doing
that and thinking something else? Yeah, but like there's very concrete evidence
that the person is actually being shaped and guided by your instruction.
So you can see this person as maybe almost if you want
to frame it this way, either that they're doing it with the
right intent, or maybe you could even see it as that they're
they're your כלי, kli, you know, you're writing it through them is
another conceptual way of thinking about that. But even if they're writing
it, you can see through what they're doing I mean, they are
writing it physically, but even if that's how you conceptualize it, you
can see it as that it's clear they're doing it properly and
properly being guided by the right instructions and by the right intent.
And רמב"ן- Ramban so this is an assumption that's working even for
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And the problem then that תוספות Tosafot deals
with is, okay, if we think it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
גדול עומד על גביו gadol omed al gabav gets you לשמה, lishma.
but there's two other things that תוספות Tosafot says you need for
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, or he assumes you need in addition to
that it being written לשמה. lishma. He says, number one, don't you
need that the סופר sofer be a שליח shaliach of the בעל?
ba'al? Like the בעל ba'al has to be מצוה השליח metzaveh hashaliach
write it for my wife and so on? Isn't that a concept
of שליחות? shlichut? So תוספות tosafot says presumably not. If this according
to this גמרא gemara that thinks a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh
ve'katan can work for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh ve'katan can't be a שליח, shaliach, תוספות tosafot, says presumably
you don't need שליחות shlichut in the writing of the גט. Get.
וכתב, vechataf, does the וכתב vechataf mean he, the husband, וכתב לה
ספר כריתות, vechataf lah sefer keritut, or does the וכתב vechataf mean
he gets somebody to write it? It's sort of like what we're
about to do the סוגיא sugya of ברית מילה berit milah in
the ישיבה, yeshiva, right? And the big question is, you know, when
the מוהל mohel says, "Okay, make me a שליח, shaliach, you know,
to do the to do the ברית מילה." berit milah. And some
fathers, you know, big חכמים, chachamim, they decide they're going to do
it themselves. And they get this because oh, it says... I'm supposed
to do it, and a lot of פוסקים poskim say, no, it's
not you're supposed to do the physical act, you gotta get somebody
to do it. Right? When it says המול לכם כל זכר imol
lachem kol zachar it doesn't mean you actually take the scalpel in
your own hand. It means you gotta get it done. Okay, so
here,
anyway, the fundamental מצוה mitzvah is to oversee as opposed to to
do. So here too, is וכתב לה v'chasav la mean you the
man write? Or does it mean get a גט Get written for
your wife? So anyway, תוספות tosafot says according to this idea that
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan works for רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
it makes it clear that you don't need a concept of שליחות.
shlichus. And the whole reason the husband says to the סופר sofer
and is מצוה metzaveh the סופר, sofer, write it for my wife,
is just to create the proper mindset and context of לשמה. lishma.
That he has to hear from the man that he wants to
divorce his wife and that he's expressing his desire, so it could
be properly assumed to be that in his writing he genuinely is
doing it for the sake of divorce and the wife. If you
didn't hear it straight from the husband, how can you really say
that you had that right intent in the writing? Okay, so the
expression of that is not to create שליחות, shlichus, it's to allow
the סופר sofer to properly do it לשמה. lishma. Okay, and therefore
it can work with a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan with
גדול עומד על גביו, gadol omed al gabav, even though you can't
have שליחות, shlichus, but if גדול עומד על גביו gadol omed al
gabav can help provide לשמה. lishma The husband would still have to
say write it for my wife to create the לשמה lishma, context,
but you don't need שליחות. shlichus. The other thing, one minute, I'll
take questions, I want to say one other point. The other thing,
I'm trying to summarize this huge תוספות, tosafot but the other point
that תוספות tosafot makes is, okay, fine, you don't need שליחות, shlichus,
but doesn't the גמרא gemara say it multiple times and we're about
to say it at the bottom of this עמוד today, that you
need בני כריתות? bnei krisus? That people that create the חפצא cheftza
of the גט Get. have to be in the פרשה parsha of
גיטין. gittin. Okay?
And חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan are not in the פרשה
parsha of גיטין. gittin. So תוספות Tosafot says well, maybe they are
in the פרשה parsha of גיטין gittin because the קטן katan will
grow up, maybe they could get better, you know, חרש ושוטה, cheresh
v'shoteh, maybe they are theoretically in the פרשה parsha of גיטין. gittin.
But the גמרא gemara, in a minute is going to suggest that
even a נכרי nochri can do it. And a נכרי, nochri,
are they relevant to the laws of גיטין? gittin? Do they
comprehend what? No, no, no. Are they covered by the legal category
of the laws of גיטין וקידושין? gittin v'kiddushin?
Like a גוי goy in
this case?
Yeah, they could effect a marriage and a divorce on their own,
okay. So, but the point is נכרים nochrim are clearly not considered
to be בני כריתות bnei krisus in that הלכתי category of גיטין
וקידושין. gittin v'kiddushin, Of our גיטין וקידושין, gittin v'kiddushin. their own yes,
but not ours. And the גמרא gemara is going to suggest that
a נכרי nochri could write the גט. Get. So תוספות Tosafot says
it must be that even when the גמרא gemara says you have
an idea of being בני כריתות, bnei krisus, that's only a requirement
if you need שליחות. shlichus. For somebody to be a שליח, shaliach,
they have to be in the פרשה. parsha. Okay, they have to
be, but for, or maybe for somebody to be a witness, they
have to be in the פרשה. parsha. So but from this גמרא,
gemara if this גמרא gemara is working with רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
which he assumes that it is because for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
you don't need any of this stuff, then what we see is,
number one, חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan can have לשמה, lishma
that's clearly what the גמרא Gemara is proving. Number two, assuming, number
two is you don't need שליחות shlichus for רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
in the writing of a גט. get. And number three is, you
don't even need the person who writes the גט get. to be
בני כריתות. bnei krisus. The whole discussion of בני כריתות bnei krisus
is a type of requirement if you need a שליח. shaliach. But
if in the writing of the גט get you don't need a
שליח, shaliach, then even a נכרי nochri can do it, you don't
need בני כריתות. bnei krisus. Okay, and that, so it becomes a
radical idea for רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that even though he very
much emphasizes the writing of the גט, get, okay, to be written
by somebody who is not a שליח shaliach of the husband and
is not even in the category of גיטין וקידושין. gittin v'kiddushin, Okay,
that's the גמרא's Gemara current assumption, assuming that we're reading this according
to רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. Now there have been some questions.
I don't understand about this idea of גדול עומד על גביו gadol
omed al gabav to make sure that whoever is writing it is
writing לשמה lishma, about whatever it is
and is having the right intent.
What do you mean by right intent?
Meaning that this is for this particular woman. Now it's an interesting
question about
with the שוטה shoteh and a קטן. katan. What, you suppose they
have to understand?
No, so that's what's called
is כוונתם ניכרת מתוך מעשיהם. kavanatam nikeret mitoch maaseihem.
That since you say we're going to, it's going to be divorced
for this man's wife, her name is לאה בת רחל, Leah bas
Rachel, write לאה בת רחל Leah bas Rachel and have in mind
that it's for this man's wife.
So it's not as much that they, someone can read it. Because
the גמרא Gemara. might get my 10-year-old to read it, oh, it
says לאה בת רחל, Leah bas Rachel, it means whoever the סופר
sofer wrote must have known. That wouldn't work. Meaning you'd still need
the גדול, gadol, even meaning, anyone can read a גט, get right?
What do you mean read it? In other words the writing it.
No, I know, but in other words, what I'm just trying to
understand if it's just a matter of just writing לאה בת רחל,
Leah bas Rachel, then I can have my 10-year-old read it afterwards,
so why do I even need the גדול? gadol? The סופר sofer
could tell.
The גדול gadol is telling the קטן katan who it's being written
for, what words to write to fill in the blanks, and that
when they're writing those words they should have certain intent in mind.
And we are assuming that since they're following the instructions of writing
the right words, they're also following the instructions of having had that
person in mind when it was being written.
You need the
גדול עומד על גביו gadol omed al gabav is to ensure that
the person is, a, doing it correctly, but also, b... so being
led by instructions that are telling them what to be thinking about.
And you'd assume that a קטן Katan couldn't do that either? In
other words, I tell a ten year old, go tell the other...
Oh, I see. I see. Why couldn't you... Oh, I see your
question. Why can't you have a קטן Katan tell a קטן Katan
or something? Well, if the problem is that a person without the
גדול עומד על גבו Gadol Omed Al Gabo is assumed to not
have the right intent. Look, it's one of two things. Either you
assume that without the גדול, Gadol, you can't trust the person to
be communicating the proper necessary intent, or like you're saying, well let's
say I hear, I hear the person say those words. I'm not
a גדול עומד על גבו Gadol Omed Al Gabo and I just
hear a קטן Katan writing and saying, I am writing this for
לאה בת רחל Leah bat Rachel who I know is שמעון'ס Shimon's
wife and she's that nice woman down the street that always gives
me cookies and I'm writing this because I know that she's going
to get divorced, right? So do you need a גדול עומד על
גבו Gadol Omed Al Gabo in that case? So that's a good
question. I think that gets to the question of whether גדול עומד
על גבו Gadol Omed Al Gabo is just to sort of create
the right mindset and then in theory you could imagine cases when
you don't need it. Or the other thing I pointed out is
you could see a גדול עומד על גבו Gadol Omed Al Gabo
as essentially the גדול Gadol is writing it through the other person
and ultimately they're seen as an extension or as the vehicle of
the גדול'ס Gadol's writing, which might be a way to solve some
of תוספות'ס Tosafot's problems as well. That maybe you could see this
person as just like the extended pen of the גדול Gadol but
ultimately it's the גדול Gadol who's really doing the writing. Although תוספות
Tosafot does not go that direction. If you emphasize that the person
him or herself can do it, then in theory you're right. It
could be done presumably without a גדול Gadol in some scenarios. Okay,
there was another question, yes?
Mechanics and intent in terms of mechanics. I mean
I could propose a kind of a Get Turing test. Right.
I understood the reference. Yes, I understand. So the גמרא Gemara sometimes
calls that כוונתו ניכרת מתוך מעשיו, kavanato nikeret mitoch maasav, but you're
right, it's not necessarily true. You're absolutely correct. So I think there
are a lot of unresolved questions about this. Okay. All right, ready?
Last one and then we have to move on.
Stencil in a way, stencil's like taking a person who can't sign
their...
Yeah,
but that's just the mechanics as opposed to... You're right, I hear
the mechanics are good, it's the intent that's the problem. That's like
almost the flip side where you don't question the person's intent, we
question their ability to do the mechanics.
Also how can a חרש Cheresh receive
that
instruction if they can't hear? Oh, that's a good point. That's a
good point. Yes, how are you instructing? I mean you could I
guess instruct with like written, like placards or something but, yeah,
in those days it really wasn't...
Yeah, it's a good question. I'm not sure the גמרא'ס Gemara's unpacked
that. Yeah, I certainly haven't. Okay, let's take a look. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so it's גדול עומד על גבו Gadol
Omed Al Gabo and that's going to somehow work even for רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman,
so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's
true, עובד כוכבים וישראל עומד על גבו הכי נמי דכשר? oved kochavim
v'Yisrael omed al gabo hachi nami d'kasher? Would you say even a
non-Jew would be good if you're saying a גדול עומד על גבו
Gadol Omed Al Gabo can create the right intent, would you say
even about a non-Jew? And again, bracketing that that might be a
special concern of בני כריתות bnei kritut that's not an issue for
the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא הכי נמי,
v'chi teima hachi nami, yeah, why not? והתניא, ve-hatanya, but we have
a ברייתא Braita that says עובד כוכבים פסול. oved kochavim pasul. So
he's not good. So what's the difference? Why are חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh v'katan good with גדול עומד על גבו Gadol Omed Al
Gabo and not an עובד כוכבים? oved kochavim? So the גמרא Gemara
says עובד כוכבים אדעתא דנפשיה עביד. oved kochavim ada'ata d'nafsheih avid. No,
he's always considered to act be acting independently. He's never considered to
be, he's a גדול, Gadol, right? So he's never considered to be
just being shaped by your intent.
Now this works very well if you think that the issue is
is that like, that this the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan
are just an extension of me. So if they're, so then I
can be, they're minors or they're not fully בני דעה, bnei deah,
I can be seen as the primary actor here and I'm doing
it through them. But if I have an adult non-Jew, I am
not doing it through him. I can tell him whatever I want
to tell him, but he's ultimately he's the one writing it. That's
אדעתא דנפשיה. ada'ata d'nafsheih. Okay. And that therefore makes it a problem
because in the end, it has to be written by me, by
an adult Jew. And in the other cases they were, I was
writing it through them. But in the non-Jew he's writing it himself.
That's a nice way of understanding what the problem of אדעתא דנפשיה
עביד ada'ata d'nafsheih avid means. It doesn't mean that, oh, להכעיס, l'hachis,
he's going to be thinking about some something else even though I'm
telling him לאה בת רחל, Leah bat Rachel, he's just doing his
own thing. Okay. But the simple, so what I said is an
I think a very nice way of understanding this, that it's a
question about am I doing it through the person or is the
person doing it? Assuming the issue is just whether the person himself
or herself has לשמה, lishma then what it's saying is is that
you can't trust, you don't know what the intent is of an
adult non-Jew. A minor we can say they're, they're, what's going on
in their head is completely being filled by what I'm saying and
therefore they're having the right intent. And by a non-Jew you can't
assume that. So there's going to be a לשמה lishmah.
problem. You mean you assume they are
להכעיס l'hachis as opposed to another Jew? Something like that. Now תוספות
Tosafot, says it's not exactly להכעיס, l'hachis, but תוספות Tosafot raises a
question. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot עובד כוכבים אדעתא דנפשיה קא
עביד, oved kochavim ada'ata d'nafsheih ka avid, תוספות Tosafot says I mean
again, it would be so funny, why would he be doing it
להכעיס? l'hachis? So תוספות Tosafot says
תימא לרי דבפרק אין מעמידין בעי רבי יהודה מילה לשמה ואפילו הכי
קתני ימול ארמאי ולא אמר דאדעתא דנפשיה קא עביד. Teima l'Ri d'be-perek
Ein Ma'amidin ba'ei Rabbi Yehuda mila lishma v'afilu hachi katani yamul Armai
v'lo amar d'ada'ata d'nafsheih ka avid. And Rabbi Yehuda... It means not
like he had something else in mind, means you know he doesn't
have anything in mind. You're saying you do it for רחמנא, Rachmana,
but he's not thinking oh I have to have כוונה kavanah לשם
leshem גר ger לשם leshem whatever. You want me to write words,
I'll write words, but I'm not having anything particular in mind, okay?
וגבי גט סתם לאו לשמה קאי, v'gabei get stam lav lishmah kai,
by גט, get, doing it without anything in mind is not
good, כדאמרינן בזבחים kedamrinan bizvachim דסתם אישה לאו לגירושין עומדת. distam isha
lav legerushin omedet. אבל מילה סתם לשמה קאי, aval milah stam lishmah
kai, כדאמרינן בזבחים, kedamrinan bizvachim, סתם לשמה קאי. stam lishmah kai. By
a מילה milah the problem is having negative כוונה, kavanah, so we
assume that a non-Jew doesn't have negative כוונה, kavanah, but he doesn't
have positive כוונה kavanah either. Okay, so חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh
vekatan we're assuming they'll have in mind, he said it has to
be for the sake of affecting a divorce and this woman is
getting divorced, they'll have those ideas in mind if I put them
in their head. You know what they say: the next time I
want your opinion I'll give it to you. So they'll have
those... Okay, so whatever ideas they have in their head are the
ideas I put in there and they'll have the right לשמה. lishmah.
But non-Jew, he might follow instructions and write the right words, but
we can't assume he'll have the right ideas in his head. Okay,
so that's the גמרא's Gemara answer.
Is this related to the question of whether a חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh vekatan should be a שליח? shaliach?
No, that's more of a formal issue. תוספות says this because no,
so the answer is no, we'll see that. This is assuming you
don't need שליחות, shlichut, that's the point that תוספות made, you just
need לשמה.
lishmah? Isn't there a fundamental difference between these different types of לשמה?
lishmah? I mean, I would think before that this idea that
you have to verify, establish the facts, and so on, doesn't really
apply to let's say סתם לשמה, stam lishmah, it's just a ritual
לשמה?
lishmah, Right, exactly.
Yes,
it's you know what else do you do? Right, like you mentioned,
you say right words, say right words, that's that.
Exactly, so that's part of the סתם לשמה קאי. stam lishmah kai.
If you're doing basically a ritual act, we could sort of say
that it almost self-defines and its intent is very minimal in terms
of what's required, I mean you know only a bad intent would
redefine or something of that...
Ritual act of writing.
Well yes, but it's also creating an instrument. Anyway, yeah. So okay,
so that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. The גמרא's Gemara answer is, okay,
עובד כוכבים אדעתא דנפשיה עביד. oved kochavim adaitya denafshaya avid. So
a non-Jew is still not good, he's still not considered to write
it with the right things in mind, or he's certainly not just
your instrument. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara. says, הדר אמר רב נחמן,
hadar amar Rav Nachman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman said לאו מילתא היא
דאמרי, lav milta hi de'amri, you know what I said? I take
back what I said. דמכדי קפסל ליה עובד כוכבים מן המובא, dimichdi
kapaslei oved kochavim min hamuva, the next משנה's Mishnah going to say
that a non-Jew cannot be a שליח shaliach to deliver a גט.
get, So since it only excludes him from being a שליח shaliach
to deliver a גט, get. מכלל דלענין כתיבה כשר, michlal d'le'inyan ktiva
kashar,
so implicitly he would be good for the writing of a גט.
get Okay, so he says you know what, I take it back.
Actually, I think a non-Jew is also good for the writing of
a גט, get and just like because it's גדול עומד על גביו
gadol omed al gabav and that'll work for a non-Jew. So והתניא
עובד כוכבים פסול? vehatanya oved kochavim pasul?
How about the fact that the ברייתא braita says that a non-Jew
is not good? How do you explain that? So ההיא רבי אליעזר
היא hahi Rabbi Eliezer hi דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. de'amar eidei mesirah
kratei.
No, no, no, that's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says that it's
about the, that it's about the עדים eidim who are present when
it's given over, those are the key עדים, not the עדים who
sign. So if it's the signatures that isn't important, what's important? ובעינן
כתיבה לשמה, uba'inan ktiva lishmah, and the writing actually needs to be
done for the right reason. והכא ודאי עובד כוכבים אדעתא דנפשיה קעביד
vehacha vadai oved kochavim adaitya denafshaya ka'avid
and the non-Jew is totally acting on his own. So meaning what?
Meaning that what he's now saying is how we read the משנה
Mishnah before. Drop this whole גדול עומד על גביו. gadol omed al
gabav. I'm going to assume from the משנה Mishnah חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh vekatan is good and a non-Jew is good. Okay, but
why, how could they be good? You know why they're good? Because
it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't care how
the גט get is being... forget this whole גדול עומד על גביו,
gadol omed al gabav, it's all רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, we don't
care how it's read, how it's written. And the ברייתא braita that
says a non-Jew is not good, that ברייתא braita is רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, and for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh vekatan would also be not good. So okay, the whole world
has now gone back in alignment, okay? It's very easy, forget this
whole גדול עומד על גביו, gadol omed al gabav, the משנה Mishnah.
that everybody is good, חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, non-Jew, is
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, we don't care how it's read, how it's
written. And the ברייתא braita that a non-Jew is not good and
also חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan presumably would be not good,
and even with גדול עומד על גביו, gadol omed al gabav, that's
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer cares how it's written.
Okay, could theoretically the גט get could theoretically
be printed off a computer?
Sure, totally, exactly, no, you don't even have to fill in the
תורף, toref, you could do the whole thing off of a printer
and just have the עדים sign it according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, ובלבד לשמה. ubilvad lishmah. Okay, and ודאי, vadai, now the גמרא
Gemara says okay, so one way now, one way of reading this
line ודאי vadai is a challenge. ודאי? vadai? I'll read it that
way, makes it more dramatic. עובד כוכבים אדעתא דנפשיה קעביד? oved kochavim
adaitya denafshaya ka'avid? One minute, even according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
how can he let a non-Jew write the גט? get And a
non-Jew is just a סתם Stam acting on his own. Don't we
care a little bit how the גט get is written according to
רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? And the answer is no. אמר רב נחמן
אמר רבי מאיר Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbi Meir because רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir used to say, אפילו מצאו באשפה, afilu metza'o ba'ashpah, you
can find it thrown in the garbage, it was even written for
a different רחל בת לאה, Rachel bat Leah, and it was thrown
in the garbage, or it was written for practice, חתמו ונתנו לו
כשר, chasmo venasno lo kasher,
just sign it with the right intent, you're good. It's all about
the signing. Until it's signed, it's a piece of paper. The signing
is what turns it into a גט, get. and it's only the
signing that matters. So now, we have two explanations of the משנה.
Mishnah One is, it's with גדול עומד על גביו, gadol omed al
gabav, it works for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which is a חידוש
chidush that לשמה, lishmah. you don't need שליחות, shlichus, you don't need
בני כריתות, bnei krisus, etc. And the other is, and maybe even
a non-Jew would be good. And the other is that no, that
all these people would be no good for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
maybe even גדול עומד על גביו, gadol omed al gabav, none of
this would be good according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Our משנה
Mishnah is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן. Eiseivei Rava le-Rav Nachman. רבא Rava
asked רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. וכתב לה לשמה. Vechasav lah lishmah. It
says you should write
לשמה. lishmah? מאי לאו כתיבת הגט, Mai lav kesivas haget, isn't this
the writing of the גט? get? Shouldn't רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, okay,
it's one thing he says signatures turn it into a גט, but
shouldn't he also make a requirement in terms of how it's written?
Shouldn't רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir require that it be written לשמה? lishmah
How can you take this גט out of the garbage pan? How
can you go ahead and have a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh
vekaton write a גט? So doesn't it, מאי לאו כתיבת הגט, mai
lav kesivas haget, doesn't the גט have to be לשמה lishmah even
according to רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? לא, חתימת עדים, Lo, chasimas edim,
no, write it for her means the writing that turns it into
a גט. It means signing it. The writing does not matter. איתיביה
רבא, Eiseivei Rava, so רבא Rava challenged, כל גט שנכתב שלא לשום
אשה פסול. kol get shenichtav shelo lishum ishah pasul. The משנה Mishnah,
says
any גט written not for the sake of the woman is invalid.
So you see it needs לשמה lishmah, and talks about writing. אימא
שנחתם שלא לשום אשה. Eima shenichtam shelo lishum ishah.
Writing doesn't mean writing, it means it was signed. Again, it's the
signing that matters.
Which one is next?
But yeah okay. איתיביה, Eiseivei, אביי Abaye asked him again. כשהוא כותבו
לשמה, Keshu kotevo lishmah, from this later משנה, Mishnah. כשהוא כותבו לשמה.
keshu kotevo lishmah.
When you write some of it, it's like you wrote all of
it, ולשמה. ulishmah. What does that mean? מאי לאו, Mai lav, does
it not mean כשהוא כותבו לשמה, keshu kotevo lishmah, as long as
you write the essential
part לשמה, lishmah. כשהוא כותבו לשמה, keshu kotevo lishmah, it's like you
wrote the whole thing לשמה. lishmah, So you see though as long
as part of the writing, the key part of the writing was
לשמה, lishmah. it all works. But you need the key part of
the writing to be לשמה. lishmah. It's about the writing has to
be לשמה. lishmah, So לא, lo, no, don't read it that way.
Read it, כשהוא חתמו לשמה, keshu chasmo lishmah, as long as you
sign it לשמה, lishmah. כשהוא כותבו לשמה, keshu kotevo lishmah, that's like
you wrote the whole thing לשמה. lishmah, You've transformed it into a
גט.
Because signing is a form of writing. Well yeah, not so fundamental
about,
well correct, but it's still not the פשט pshat of the word
כותבו, kotevo, which is the text of the גט. Still, okay, so
anyway we're saying that you have these ברייתות משניות beraitot mishnayot later
on that speak about the writing being לשמה, lishmah? so how could
you say all that matters is the signing? And the answer is
yeah, writing means signing. אי בעית אימא, Iy ba'is eima, if you
want you could say an easier answer. הני מתניתין מני רבי אליעזר
היא, Hani masnitin mani Rabbi Eliezer hi, דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. de'amar
edei mesirah karsi. Fine, what type of proof was that? I mean,
the פסוק pasuk is a question, okay, but those משניות, mishnayot, that's
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position. Are there משניות mishnayot that say that
you need the writing to be לשמה? lishmah, Sure, that's רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer position. We're talking within רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, so
for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the writing has to be לשמה, lishmah.
or at least the תורף toref has to be לשמה. lishma A
חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekaton, a non-Jew would not be good,
presumably even גדול עומד על גביו. gadol omed al gabav. And we're
talking within רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that we don't care how it's
written, we only care how it's
signed. אי בעית אימא, Iy ba'is eima, now here's answer number three.
So we have two first two answers of this משנה. Mishnah. Number
one, it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and גדול עומד על גביו. gadol
omed al gabav. Number two, it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Here's explanation
number three of this משנה. Mishnah. אי בעית אימא Iy ba'is eima
if you want I can
say, הני מתניתין מני רבי אליעזר היא. hani masnitin mani Rabbi Eliezer
hi. רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, so answer number
three. רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel says here's a
new way of reading the
משנה. Mishnah, אמר שמואל והוא ששייר מקום התורף. Amar Shmuel vehu sheshiyer
makom hatoref. It's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Why do I, how do
I solve the problem that it's written שלא לשמה shelo lishmah according
to רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? How does a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh vekaton do it? Because they're not writing, they're not filling in
the lines, they're just writing the boilerplate. As long as you leave
the key lines blank and let a גדול gadol fill in those
key lines, they can write the
boilerplate. It could
be the
printer. Exactly. וכן אמר רבי חגא משמיה משמיה דעולא והוא ששייר מקום
התורף. Vechein amar Rabbi Chaga mishmeih mishmeih de-Ulla vehu sheshiyer makom hatoref.
רבי אליעזר היא, Rabbi Eliezer hi, he is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
ורב זירא אמר רבי יוחנן אין התורה. Ve-Rav Zeira amar Rabbi Yochanan
ein hatorah. No, that's not the right teaching. מאי אין התורה, Mai
ein hatorah, what does that mean? אמר רבי אבא כאן הודיעך שאין
כח לשמה, Amar Rabbi Abba kan hodi'ach she'ein koach lishmah, ורבי מאיר
היא. ve-Rabbi Meir hi. The whole point of the משנה, Mishnah if
the משנה Mishnah wanted to say it's good as long as they
leave over the blank lines, it should have said they need to
leave over. over the key lines. The point of the משנה Mishnah
is to say we don't care who writes the גט. חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan can write the גט. The point of the
משנה Mishnah is telling you the writing of the גט is immaterial.
Okay, so the only real way of reading this משנה Mishnah is
רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. The משנה Mishnah. is very blanket, חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan can write a גט, it's telling you the
writing of the גט doesn't matter. Okay, כאן דיחוס, kanno d'yuchas, אין
כוח לשמה, ein koach lishma, we don't care about the לשמה of
the גט, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir היא, hi, דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי.
d'amar eidi chatimah karsai. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן,
v'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rebbi Yochanan, רבי אליעזר היא. Rebbi
Eliezer hi. But we just had another teaching that it was רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer in the name of
רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. So אמר רב עינא amar Rav Ina אליבא
דרבי יוחנן. aliba d'Rebbi Yochanan. Fine, two versions of how רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan explains the משנה. Mishnah. So we have three readings of
the משנה. Mishnah One, it's רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and גדול עומד
על גביו. gadol omeid al gabav. Of course, then it should have
said גדול עומד על גביו. gadol omeid al gabav. Number two, if
it's רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and you're only writing the טופס, tofes,
not the תורף, toref, then it should have said that you're not
filling in the תורף. toref. So the third reading is clearly the
strongest reading, which is the משנה Mishnah. is saying it doesn't matter
who writes the גט, and that is רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. All
that matters is who signs, it doesn't matter who writes. Okay, next
משנה. Mishnah.
What was the last word of רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? אמוראי נינהו.
amora'ei ninhu.
It's a debate of אמוראים Amora'im how רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan explained
the משנה. Mishnah. Right. Okay, next משנה. Mishnah And this is the
משנה Mishna that was referred to a minute ago. הכל כשרים להביא
את הגט חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן. Hakol kshirim l'havi es haget chutz
m'cheresh shoteh v'katan. Everybody can bring a גט. Now we're clearly dealing
with שליחות. shlichus. So except for חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan
who can't be a שליח. shaliach. Okay, וסומא, v'suma, a blind person,
why not? We'll find out in a minute. ועובד כוכבים, v'oved kochavim,
and a non-Jew who also is excluded from שליחות. shlichus. Now קיבלו
קטן והגדיל, kiblo katan v'higdil, let's say you gave the גט to
a קטן katan while he was a minor and then he became
an adult. Okay, but he was appointed as a minor and it
was given to him as a minor. חרש ונתפקח, cheresh v'nitpakeach, or
gave it to a deaf-mute who then became better. סומא ונתפתח, suma
v'nitpateach, or a blind person whose sight was restored. שוטה ונשתפה, shoteh
v'nishtapeh, or a שוטה shoteh who then became of right mind. עובד
כוכבים ונתגייר, oved kochavim v'nisgeiyer, or a non-Jew who converted. פסול, pasul,
it's invalid. The appointment of the שליחות shlichus has to be when
the person is in the category of being a שליח. shaliach. If
they were appointed as a שליחות shlichus and it was given to
them prior then they cannot become, then they can't, you know, you
would need to reappoint them as a שליח. shaliach. It's invalid. אבל
פקח ונתחרש וחזר ונתפקח, Aval pikeach v'nitcharesh v'chazar v'nitpakeach, it was given
to a person when they were well and they became a חרש
cheresh and then they became well, but it's ABA, they were, it
was good, they became bad and became good. פתוח ונסתמא וחזר ונתפתח,
Patuach v'nistama v'chazar v'nitpateach, or sighted became blind and then became sighted.
שפוי ונשתטה וחזר ונשתפה, Shafui v'nishtateh v'chazar v'nishtapeh, okay, well and became
a שוטה shoteh and then well again. In all those cases כשר,
kasher, it's okay, even though there was a period in the middle
where it was not good. זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the
principle, כל שתחילתו וסופו בדעת כשר. kol shetechilaso v'sofo b'daas kasher. As
long as they had דעת daas at the beginning and the end
it's good. We don't say that every step while they're on the
plane, if they you know every step along the way, if they
received it from the husband properly and delivered it to the wife
when they were in the right state of mind or in the,
you know, had the right status. The fact that it got conveyed
while they were in some problematic status does not somehow invalidate. The
key is how it was received from the husband and how it
was delivered to the wife.
And the reason we need, I felt like you know,
if you either have עדי מסירה, eidi mesirah, in which case who
cares about the שליח? shaliach?
What do you mean? The person has to be a שליח. shaliach.
What do you mean who cares? In order to represent the husband
he has to be a שליח. shaliach. He has to be a
בר דעת. bar daas. He has to follow the laws of שליחות.
shlichus.
So the husband specifically is the one who
he's ממנה m'maneh him as a שליח. shaliach.
Okay, so the husband is ממנה m'maneh someone שליח, shaliach, it's really
important. Meaning if you say עדי מסירה כרתי, eidi mesirah karsai, you
could say like you know I don't really care who gives it,
as long as the get gets to them and you know I
have my witnesses over there.
No, no, no, but he has to be well. The question becomes
can I send a גט through the mail and appoint somebody as
a שליח שלא בפניו? shaliach shelo b'fanav? So basically, so I'm going
to deliver it by a non-Jew or whatever, I'm just going to
you know I don't know, put it on the back of a
camel, and the camel's going to bring it to you Michael and
you'll be my שליח, shaliach, and I'm saying Michael when you get
this גט actually and you open it up and there's a letter,
a cover letter, and the cover letter says when you get this
גט I'm appointing you as a שליח shaliach to give this גט
to my wife, can that count? So that maybe the answer is
yes. Okay. Okay, but you have to be when you receive the,
the שליח shaliach has to get the appointment from the husband and
he has to be in a status of being a כשר שליח
kasher shaliach when he receives the appointment, and then he has to
be able
to deliver it in the right state to the woman. When the
husband gives to the שליח shaliach and the שליח shaliach is fine
all
the way through, but after the husband gave the גט the husband
became, oh that's a problem. Yeah, that's a problem. The husband also
has to be in a state to be able to divorce his
wife. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara בשלמא חרש
שוטה וקטן, Bishlama cheresh shoteh v'katan, so I understand חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh v'katan דלאו בני דעה נינהו, d'lav bnei deiah ninhu, they
can't be good because they're not בני דעה. bnei deiah. עובד כוכבים,
Oved kochavim, a non-Jew, נמי דלאו בר היתירה הוא, nami d'lav bar
heiteira hu, sometimes that's called לאו בני כריתות lav bnei krisus or
לאו בני היתירה. lav bnei heiteira. He's not in the position to
מתיר matir a woman, meaning he is not in the category of
the הלכות halachos of גיטין וקידושין, gittin v'kiddushin, of our הלכות halachos
of גיטין וקידושין, gittin v'kiddushin, and therefore cannot serve as a... agent
as a שליח. shaliach. So here's the idea that בני כריתות benei
kritut is part of a requirement of being a legitimate שליח. shaliach.
You have to be in the פרשה parsha to be able to
represent me. Okay. אלא סומא אמאי לא? Ella Suma amai lo? Why
can a blind person not be a שליח? shaliach? They're they're considered
a בר דעת. bar da'as. So אמר רב ששת לפי שאינו יודע
ממי נוטלה ולמי נותנה לו. Amar Rav Sheshet lefi she'eino yode'a miman
notlah ulemi notnah lo. So רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, who I believe
himself was blind, right, interestingly gives the answer because you don't know
who you're getting it from and who you're giving it to. He
hears the voice. Well, that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to answer.
Okay. So therefore, right, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to
answer. So anyway, so therefore, maybe even if by chance you did
give it to the right person, maybe he feels that you're not
a legitimate שליח shaliach if you're not able to really control and
know enough of what's happening in your in what you're doing. So
the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף לה רב יוסף. matkif lah Rav Yosef.
So רב יוסף Rav Yosef who was also blind, right? I think
this is very interesting from what I remember both רב ששת Rav
Sheshet and רב יוסף Rav Yosef were blind. Not at the same
time. Well, okay. But I think רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, I think
the גמרא about מאן אמרי אגדתא בבי רב ששת ובבי רב יוסף,
man amri aggadata be-vei Rav Sheshet u-vei Rav Yosef, they who said
the הגדה haggada there has cause they were both blind. Anyway, so
he says if that's true, היכא סומא מותר באשתו? heich suma muttar
be-ishto? So how can a blind person have sex, a blind man
have sex with his wife if you don't know who you know
if you say oh you're blind you don't know who you're dealing
with? והיכא בני אדם מותרין בנשיהם לילה? Ve-heich benei adam muttarin bi-nsheichem
lailah? How can anybody have man have sex with his wife at
night when it's dark? אלא בטביעותא דקלא. Ella bitzi'uta de-kala. It must
be because you can recognize, I had to love the metaphor, you
have you have sight recognition of their voice. Okay, טביעותא, tzi'uta, but
it means do you recognize voices? הכא נמי בטביעותא דקלא. Hacha nami
bitzi'uta de-kala. Here too you can recognize voices. So that's not an
answer. אלא אמר רב יוסף, Ella amar Rav Yosef,
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef says here's why a blind person can't
do it. הכא בחוץ לארץ עסקינן, Hacha be-chutz la-aretz askinan, we're dealing
in חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz, דבעי למימר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, de-ba'ei
le-meimar bifanay nichtav u-vifanay nechtam, because you have to say it was
written signed and written and sealed in front of me and and
written and signed in front of me. ולא מצי למימר, Ve-lo matzi
le-meimar, and he can't say it because even if it was physically
present, the בפני bifanay means that he saw it being written and
signed. Not necessarily you have the טביעותא דקלא tzi'uta de-kala of the
scratching. Yeah but apparently he's right so this the גמרא's apparently assuming
that that idea of hearing the scratching is in a case where
you could see it. Okay. So despite the עבידא לגלויי avida li-giluy
type of thing. Right, but he's assuming that you can't say בפני
נכתב bifanay nichtav even with טביעותא דקלא tzi'uta de-kala unless you actually
have seen it. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye said
אלא מעתה, ella me-atah, if that's true the only problem is saying
בפני נכתב. bifanay nichtav. פתוח ונסתמא הא דמצי אמר הכי. Patuach ve-nistamma
ha de-matzi amar hachi. הכא נמי דכשר. Hacha nami de-kasher. So if
somebody who had sighted when it was when it was signed and
then he became blind before he delivered the גט. Would you say
that that would be כשר kosher because you could say בפני נכתב,
bifanay nichtav, you're a good שליח shaliach and you saw it being
written so you could say that? והכא נמי דכשר? Ve-hacha nami de-kasher?
And presumably the answer would be sure why not? But the משנה
Mishna. says פתוח ונסתמא וחזר ונשתפה כשר. Patuach ve-nistamma ve-chazar ve-nistape'ach kasher.
Sighted and blind and then sighted is כשר. kosher. חזר ונשתפה אין,
Chazar ve-nistape'ach in, only if he becomes sighted by the end. לא
חזר ונשתפה לא, Lo chazar ve-nistape'ach lo, if he didn't become sighted
at the end it would not be כשר. kosher. So according to
you why should that be a problem? So the answer is no.
הוא הדין דאף על גב דלא חזר ונשתפה. Hu hadin de-af al
gav de-lo chazar ve-nistape'ach. You know what, even if he did not
become sighted at the end. והאי דקתני שפוי ונשתטה וחזר ונשתפה. Ve-haidi
de-tani shafuy ve-nishtateh ve-chazar ve-nishpah. Since the other examples we gave were
being of right mind and then becoming a שוטה shoteh and then
of right mind that we gave you know ABA. טעמא דחזר ונשתפה,
Ta'ama de-chazar ve-nishpah, that case you had to get to the better
state by the end. הא לא חזר ונשתטה, Ha lo chazar ve-nishtateh,
if that person did not become of right mind by the end
לא, lo, it would not be good. So those cases we did
ABA, you had to end back in that in that state. תנא
נמי פתוח ונסתמא וחזר ונשתפה. Tanna nami patuach ve-nistamma ve-chazar ve-nistape'ach. So
for like literary parallel we did sighted blind and became sighted, but
really even if the person did not become sighted at the end
it would be okay. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי
Rav Ashi says that also can be inferred by a close read
of the text דקתני זה הכלל כל שתחילתו וסופו בדעת כשר. de-tani
zeh haklal kol she-tchilato ve-sofo be-da'at kasher. It sums up those ideas
and says as long as you begin as a בר דעת bar
da'as and end as a בר דעת bar da'as you're okay. Okay
so the key is בר דעת. bar da'as. Somebody who's blind is
not a בר דעת bar da'as problem. ולא תני, Ve-lo tani, it
doesn't say כל שתחילתו וסופו בכשרות כשר. kol she-tchilato ve-sofo be-kachshrut kasher.
You have to be beginning and end in a כשר kosher state.
So if it's a בר דעת bar da'as problem then you have
to have that at the beginning and the end. If it's a
problem about being blind, that's only a beginning problem, that's not an
end problem. Okay. So that now he's explained the case of blind
in the משנה. mishna בעי מיניה מרבי אמי, Ba'ei minei mi-Rabbi Ami,
they asked רבי אמי Rabbi Ami עבד מהו שיעשה שליח לקבל גט
אשה מיד בעלה? Eved mahu she-ye'aseh shaliach le-kabbel get isha mi-yad ba'alah?
Can a slave who's not the woman's slave, if it's the woman's
slave it's like being put on her property. But if it is
ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven is divorcing רחל, Rachel, can שמעון Shimon slave
be רחל's Rachel שליח? shaliach? Or can he be ראובן's Reuven שליח?
shaliach? רש"י Rashi said you're going to ask it either way. Can
a slave who's not owned by either party here, is that slave
כשר kosher as a שליח shaliach for bringing or receiving a גט?
עבד כנעני. Eved Kena'ani.
Okay.
He's partly חייב במצוות, chayyav be-mitzvot, right, is that enough? And a
non-Jew is out
of
the category. Is an עבד eved in? An עבד eved does not...
So can they be a שליח shaliach or not? So, so, אמרו
ליה מדקתני פסול ועכו"ם בחדא, amru lei midkatanei pasul ve'akum be'chada, since
the משנה mishna, only invalidated a non-Jew,
מכלל דעבד כשר, michlal de'eved kasher, we can infer that a slave
would be כשר. kasher. אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן אין עבד
נעשה שליח לקבל גט לאשה מיד בעלה. Amar Rav Assi Amar Rabbi
Yochanan ein eved na'aseh shaliach lekabbel get le'isha miyad ba'ala. No, sorry,
it won't work. Why not? לפי שאינו בתורת גיטין וקידושין, lefi she'eino
betoras gittin ve'kiddushin, because even though they're חייב chayav in מצוות, mitzvos,
as we're saying, they're not בתורת גיטין וקידושין, betoras gittin ve'kiddushin, laws
of גיטין gittin וקידושין ve'kiddushin do not apply to them because marriage
doesn't apply to slaves. Okay, even though מצוות mitzvos do, marriage doesn't
apply to slaves. So the גמרא says, מתקיף לה רבי אלעזר. maskif
lah Rabbi Elazar. So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar counters, טעמא במילתא דליתא
הא במילתא דאיתא כשר, ta'ama be'milsa d'leisa ha be'milsa d'isa kasher, meaning
he's not challenging that a slave is not כשר, kasher, he's challenging
that a slave should be even more not כשר. kasher. You're saying
the only problem with a slave is he doesn't happen to be
in those מצוות mitzvos of גיטין gittin וקידושין, ve'kiddushin, but you're saying
if other things, a slave could be a שליח shaliach for me.
Okay, as long as it wasn't an added category of law that
applied to a slave. Is that really true? Is a slave כשר
kasher as a שליח shaliach when the laws apply to them?
והא עכו"ם וכותי, ve'ha akum ve'kuti, but a non-Jew or a Samaritan,
דאיתנהו בתורת תרומה, de'isnu betoras terumah, they're in the פרשה parsha of
תרומה, terumah, they can take their own תרומה. terumah. דתנן, detnan, we
learned
in the משנה, mishna, העכו"ם והכותי שתרמו משלהם תרומתם תרומה. ha'akum ve'hakuti
shetarumu mishelahen terumasam terumah. They owned land in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
the grain grew, we will assume that their ownership of the land
did not remove from the land the קדושה, kedusha, so the grain
actually, if it's טבל, tevel, it grew in their land. And they
now are מפריש תרומה mafrish terumah on their grain in their land
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Does it have a status of תרומה?
terumah?
They don't have a חיוב chiyuv of
giving תרומה, terumah, but does it change the status of the actual
תרומה? terumah? And the answer is yes, תרומתם תרומה. terumasam terumah. So
they're in the פרשה parsha of תרומה. terumah. Okay. ודתנן, u'detnan, and
we learned in the משנה, עכו"ם שתרם של ישראל, akum shetaram shel
Yisrael, if I had a non-Jew take תרומה terumah for me, אפילו
ברשות, afilu birshus, even if I appointed him, אין תרומתם תרומה, ein
terumasam terumah, it's not good. So you see they're in the פרשה,
parsha, but nevertheless the laws apply to them, but they can't be
a שליח. shaliach. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? So it must be that
it's not sufficient to be in the פרשה parsha in terms of
the laws. There must be another basis of exclusion of why he
can't be my שליח. shaliach. So what's the reason? לאו משום דכתיב
גם אתם? lav mishum de'chsiv gam atem? It says, כן תרימו גם
אתם, kein tarimu gam atem, even you should take תרומה. terumah. So
the גם gam means your שליח shaliach can do it. But the
אתם atem means your שליח shaliach has to be like you. מה
אתם ישראל אף שלוחכם ישראל, ma atem Yisrael af sheluchachem Yisrael, that
you have to be Jewish. So if you have a non-Jew who's
in the פרשה, parsha, but nevertheless he can't be a שליח. shaliach.
Part of being a שליח shaliach is being Jewish, of being a
שליח shaliach for a Jew. So if that's true, the same should
be true by a slave, that even in an area where a
slave is in the פרשה, parsha, he should not be able to
be a שליח shaliach because he's not a ישראל. Yisrael. So we
see we have two criteria: A, you have to be a ישראל,
Yisrael, and B, you have to be in the פרשה. parsha. So
a slave should never be able to be a שליח shaliach because
he's not a ישראל, Yisrael, the same way a non-Jew can never
be a
שליח. shaliach. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, amrei d'bei Rabbi Yannai, so דבי
רבי ינאי d'bei Rabbi Yannai responded, לא, lo, no, you read the
פרשה, parsha, you read that too broadly. It's מה אתם בני ברית
אף שלוחכם בני ברית. ma atem bnei bris af sheluchachem bnei bris.
That you have to be, it's not ישראל, Yisrael, okay, which would
exclude עבדים, avadim, it's בני ברית. bnei bris. In the ברית bris
of מצוות, mitzvos, or if you want to say ברית מילה, bris
milah, at least male slaves had a ברית מילה. bris milah. So
since slaves are bound by the מצוות, mitzvos, and by the way,
an important רש"י Rashi who emphasizes the word ברית. bris. רש"י Rashi
says,
where's the רש"י? Rashi? בני ברית, bnei bris, it's about eight to
ten lines down under what it says במדבר י"ח Bamidbar yud-ches in
the margin. מהולים ובאו בברית מצוות, mehulin u'bo'ei bivris mitzvos, so there's
מהולים mehulin and מצוות. mitzvos. אף שלוחכם, af sheluchachem, at least for
the male, בני ברית, bnei bris, לאפוקי עכו"ם. le'afokei akum. Although עבד
בן ברית הוא דכתיב מחטב עציך עד שואב מימיך. eved ben bris
hu de'chsiv meichotev etzecha ad sho'ev meimecha. What's the next פסוק? pasuk?
לעברך בברית ה' אלהיך. la'avracha bivris Hashem Elokecha. So if your water
drawers are your slaves, your slaves are part of the ברית. bris.
Interesting question, is there an idea of ערבות areivus by slaves? Interesting
question about how much they are part of the עם am in
an extended sense. So they're not ישראל, Yisrael, but they're somehow part
of the עם am and they're בני ברית. bnei bris. So therefore
he's saying is there are two criteria to be a שליח: shaliach:
you have to be a בן ברית, ben bris, which includes עבדים
avadim but excludes
non-Jews. You have to be a בן ברית, ben bris, and you
have to be in that פרשה. parsha. So a slave could be
my שליח shaliach for let's say taking תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'ma'asros, but
they can't be my שליח shaliach for גיטין gittin וקידושין ve'kiddushin because
laws of גיטין gittin וקידושין ve'kiddushin don't apply. A non-Jew can't be
my שליח shaliach for anything because there's a requirement of בן ברית.
ben bris. Okay, let's read one more line.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן אין עבד נעשה שליח
לקבל גט אשה. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan ein
eved na'aseh shaliach lekabbel get isha. Same explanation. The—he's enough of a—the
בן ברית ben bris is fine, but he's—the laws of גיטין gittin
and קידושין kiddushin don't apply, and therefore cannot be a שליח. shaliach.
ואף על פי ששנינו, V'af al pi she'shaninu, הרי השפחה הזאת ולדך
בן חורין, harei hashifcha hazos v'ladach ben chorin, אם היתה עוברה זכתה
לו, im haysa ubara zachsa lo, even though we said that, I
think we're going to have to end here because we only have
one minute. Okay, so we have ended with the idea, at least
the last thing anyway is a separate point. We've ended with the
idea that to be a שליח, shaliach, you have to be a
בן דעת, ben da'as, so a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan
cannot. You have to be a בר כריתות bar krisus or you
have to be a בן ברית, ben bris, so a non-Jew not.
And a slave in theory is a בן ברית, ben bris, but
because he's not בתורה—that's be'torah like because he's not בר כריתות, bar
krisus, he's not בתורת גיטין וקידושין—that's be'toras gittin v'kiddushin why a slave
cannot be a שליח shaliach for גיטין וקידושין, but a slave could
be a שליח shaliach for something like תרומה. truma. Okay, and we
will end up tomorrow with really a different point relating to slave.
We will continue tomorrow with a different point relating to slave.